CONTACT Information Fermi National Accelerator Laboratory

Theoretical Physics Division, Astrophysics Department

Website: https://samueldmcdermott.github.io/

Email: samueldmcdermott@gmail.com

Areas of Expertise General: High-dimensional Bayesian parameter inference and uncertainty quantification; machine learning (97.25% in Andrew Ng's Coursera class, 100% on programming assignments); 1D and 2D signal analysis; wavelet transforms.

Academic: Identification of particle physics beyond the Standard Model; maximizing utility of astrophysical data sets; new physics in stars, extreme astrophysical environments, and cosmological settings.

EMPLOYMENT

## Fermi National Accelerator Laboratory

• Postdoctoral associate and associate fellow of KICP **September 2017-present** 

Schramm Fellow January 2019-present

# C. N. Yang Institute for Theoretical Physics

Postdoctoral Associate

September 2014-September 2017

Citizenship: USA

Phone: (215) 990-7036

**EDUCATION** 

Ph.D., Physics. Ratcheting up the Search for Dark Matter

The University of Michigan, Ann Arbor. Advisor: Dr. Kathryn M. Zurek

Fermi National Accelerator Laboratory. Predoctoral Theory Fellowship, 2013-2014. Supervisor: Dr. Dan Hooper

**B.A.**, Physics and **B.A.**, Math. Honors Thesis: Effect of Electric Field on Fluorescence Intermittency Statistics of CdSe Nanocrystals

December 2008

The University of Pennsylvania. Advisor: Dr. Marija Drndic

AWARDS AND RECOGNITION

#### Fermilab

- Schramm Fellowship
- Predoctoral Theory Fellowship, 2013-2014, and URA Thesis Award, 2015

### The University of Michigan

• Rackham Predoctoral Fellowship, 2013-2014

### The University of Pennsylvania

• Summa cum Laude, with Distinction in Physics; Dean's List, all semesters; Benjamin Franklin Scholar; Phi Beta Kappa scholar

Publication Statistics According to the **inSpireHEP** database, as of April 13, 2022:

- 46 research publications and 1 review article
- 9 Letters published (7 in the Physical Review, 1 in the Astrophysical Journal, 1 in Physics Letters B)
- one solicited white paper for Snowmass 2020; numerous letters of interest for Snowmass 2020 and Astro 20 Decadal
- more than 3,500 total citations
- *h*-index: 28

PUBLICATIONS Prepared while at Fermilab as a postdoctoral associate:

47. Jeremy Sakstein, Djuna Croon, and SDM. Axion Instability Supernovae. arXiv:2203.06160. FERMILAB-PUB-22-118-T.

- 46. Ilias Cholis, Yi-Ming Zhong, SDM, and Joseph P. Surdutovich. The Return of the Templates: Revisiting the Galactic Center Excess with Multi-Messenger Observations. arXiv:2112.09706 [astro-ph]. FERMILAB-PUB-21-709-T.
- 45. Marcela Carena, Nina M. Coyle, Yingying Li, SDM, and Yuhsin Tsai. *Cosmologically Degenerate Fermions*. arXiv:2108.02785. FERMILAB-PUB-21-325-T.
- 44. Susan Gardner, SDM, and Brian Yanny. The Milky Way, Coming into Focus: Precision Astrometry Probes its Evolution, and its Dark Matter. Prog. Part. Nucl. Phys. 121, 103904 (2021). arXiv:2106.13284 [astro-ph]. FERMILAB-PUB-21-297-T.
- 43. Pierce Giffin, John Lloyd, SDM, and Stefano Profumo. Neutron Star Quantum Death by Small Black Holes. arXiv:2105.06504. FERMILAB-PUB-21-259-T.
- 42. Eric J. Baxter, Djuna Croon, SDM, and Jeremy Sakstein. Find the Gap: Black Hole Population Analysis with an Astrophysically Motivated Mass Function. Astrophys. J. Lett. **916**, no.2, L16 (2021). arXiv:2104.02685 [astro-ph]. FERMILAB-PUB-21-148-T.
- 41. Carlos Blanco, Yonatan Kahn, Benjamin Lillard, and SDM, Dark Matter Daily Modulation With Anisotropic Organic Crystals. Phys. Rev. D **104**, 036011 (2021). arXiv:2103.08601. FERMILAB-PUB-21-066-T.
- 40. James M. Cline, Guillermo Gambini, SDM, and Matteo Puel, *Late-Time Dark Matter Oscillations and the Core-Cusp Problem*. JHEP **04**, 223 (2021). arXiv:2010.12583. FERMILAB-PUB-20-556-T.
- 39. Jeremy Sakstein, Djuna Croon, SDM, Maria C. Straight and Eric J. Baxter, Beyond the Standard Model Explanations of GW190521. Phys. Rev. Lett. 125, no.26, 261105 (2020). arXiv:2009.01213 [gr-qc]. FERMILAB-PUB-20-461-T.
- 38. Djuna Croon, SDM, and Jeremy Sakstein. *Missing in Action: New Physics and the Black Hole Mass Gap.* Phys. Rev. D **102**, no. 11, 115024; selected as an **Editor's Choice** article. arXiv:2007.07889 [gr-qc]. FERMILAB-PUB-20-328-T.
- 37. Djuna Croon, SDM, and Jeremy Sakstein. *Missing in Axion: where are XENON1T's big black holes?* Phys. Dark Univ. **32**, 100801 (2021). arXiv:2007.00650. FERMILAB-PUB-20-270-T.
- 36. Djuna Croon, Gilly Elor, Rebecca Leane, and SDM. Supernova Muons: New Constraints on Z' Bosons, Axions, and ALPs. JHEP **01**, 107 (2021). arXiv:2006.13942. FERMILAB-PUB-20-246-A-T.
- 35. Celeste Keith, Dan Hooper, SDM, and Nikita Blinov. Constraints on Primordial Black Holes From Big Bang Nucleosynthesis Revisited. Phys. Rev. D **102**, no.10, 103512 (2020). arXiv:2006.03608 [astro-ph]. FERMILAB-PUB-20-224-A.
- 34. Dan Hooper, Gordan Krnjaic, John March-Russell, SDM, and Rudin Petrossian-Byrne. Hot Gravitons and Gravitational Waves From Kerr Black Holes in the Early Universe. arXiv:2004.00618 [astro-ph]. FERMILAB-PUB-20-125-A-T.

33. Samuel J. Witte, Salvador Rosauro-Alcaraz, SDM, and Vivian Poulin. *Dark Photon Dark Matter in the Presence of Inhomogeneous Structure*. JHEP **06**, 132 (2020). arXiv:2003.13698 [astro-ph]. FERMILAB-PUB-20-121-T.

- 32. Yi-Ming Zhong, SDM, Ilias Cholis, and Patrick J. Fox. A New Mask for An Old Suspect: Testing the Sensitivity of the Galactic Center Excess to the Point Source Mask. Phys. Rev. Lett. **124**, no.23, 231103 (2020). arXiv:1911.12369 [astro-ph]. FERMILAB-PUB-19-575-T.
- 31. SDM and Samuel J. Witte. *The Cosmological Evolution of Light Dark Photon Dark Matter*. Phys. Rev. D **101**, 063030 (2020). arXiv:1911.05086 [hep-ph]. FERMILAB-PUB-19-565-T.
- 30. Gordan Krnjaic and SDM. *Implications of BBN Bounds for Cosmic Ray Upscattered Dark Matter*. Phys. Rev. D **101**, no.12, 123022 (2020). arXiv:1908.00007 [hep-ph]. FERMILAB-PUB-19-358-A.
- 29. Nikita Blinov, Kevin J. Kelly, Gordan Krnjaic, and SDM. Constraining the Self-Interacting Neutrino Interpretation of the Hubble Tension. Phys. Rev. Lett. 123, no. 19, 191102 (2019). arXiv:1905.02727 [astro-ph]. FERMILAB-PUB-19-175-A-T.
- 28. Dan Hooper, Gordan Krnjaic, and SDM. Dark Radiation and Superheavy Dark Matter from Black Hole Domination. JHEP **08**, 001 (2019). arXiv:1905.01301 [hep-ph]. FERMILAB-PUB-19-186-A.
- 27. SDM and Michael S. Turner. Nuclear Kinetic Equilibrium During Big Bang Nucleosynthesis. arXiv:1811.04932 [hep-ph]. FERMILAB-PUB-18-625-A
- 26. SDM, Sanjay Reddy, and Srimoyee Sen. A Deeply Bound Dibaryon is Incompatible with Neutron Stars and Supernovae. Phys. Rev. D **99**, no. 3, 035013 (2019). arXiv:1809.06765 [hep-ph]. FERMILAB-PUB-18-490-A.
- 25. Rouven Essig, SDM, Hai-Bo Yu, and Yi-Ming Zhong. Constraining Dissipative Dark Matter Self-Interactions. Phys. Rev. Lett. 123, no. 12, 121102 (2019). arXiv:1809.01144 [hep-ph]. FERMILAB-PUB-18-437-A.
- 24. Dan Hooper, Gordan Krnjaic, Andrew J. Long, and SDM. *WIMPflation*. Phys. Rev. Lett. **122**, no. 9, 091802 (2019). arXiv:1807.03308 [hep-ph]. FERMILAB-PUB-18-309-A.
- 23. Asher Berlin, Dan Hooper, Gordan Krnjaic, and SDM. Severely Constraining Dark Matter Interpretations of the 21-cm Anomaly. Phys. Rev. Lett. 121, no. 1, 011102 (2018); selected as an Editor's Choice article. arXiv:1803.02804 [hep-ph]. FERMILAB-PUB-18-066-A.
- 22. Bhaskaran Balaji, Ilias Cholis, Patrick J. Fox, and SDM. *Analyzing the Gamma-ray Sky with Wavelets*. arXiv:1803.01952 [astro-ph]. Phys. Rev. D **98**, no. 4, 043009 (2018). FERMILAB-PUB-18-057-A-T.
- 21. Jae Hyeok Chang, Rouven Essig, and SDM. Supernova 1987A Constraints on Sub-GeV Dark Sectors, Millicharged Particles, the QCD Axion, and an Axion-like Particle. JHEP **09**, 051 (2018). arXiv:1803.00993 [hep-ph]. YITP-SB-18-01, FERMILAB-PUB-17-432-T.

 Dan Hooper and SDM. Robust Constraints and Novel Gamma-Ray Signatures of Dark Matter That Interacts Strongly With Nucleons. Phys. Rev. D 97, 115006 (2018). arXiv:1802.03025 [hep-ph]. FERMILAB-PUB-18-032-A.

 SDM. Is Self-Interacting Dark Matter Undergoing Dark Fusion? Phys. Rev. Lett. 120, 221806 (2018); selected as an Editor's Choice article. arXiv:1711.00857 [hep-ph]. FERMILAB-PUB-17-483-A-T.

Prepared while at YITP Stony Brook as a postdoctoral associate:

- 18. SDM, Hiren H. Patel, and Harikrishnan Ramani. Dark Photon Decay Beyond The Euler-Heisenberg Limit. Phys. Rev. D 97, no. 7, 073005 (2018). arXiv:1705.00619 [hep-ph]. YITP-SB-17-14.
- 17. Samuel Witte, Vera Gluscevic, and SDM. Prospects for Distinguishing Dark Matter Models Using Annual Modulation. JCAP **02**, no. 02, 044 (2017). arXiv:1612.07808 [hep-ph]. YITP-SB-16-51.
- 16. Jae Hyeok Chang, Rouven Essig, and SDM. Revisiting Supernova 1987A Bounds on Dark Photons. JHEP **01**, 107 (2017). arXiv:1611.03864 [hep-ph]. YITP-SB-16-44.
- 15. SDM, Patrick Meade, and Harikrishnan Ramani. Singlet Scalar Resonances and the Diphoton Excess. Phys. Lett. B **755**, 353 (2016). arXiv:1512.05326 [hep-ph]. YITP-SB-15-47.
- 14. SDM, Ilias Cholis, Patrick J. Fox, and Samuel K. Lee. Wavelet-Based Techniques for the Gamma-Ray Sky. JCAP **07**, 07, 045, (2016). arXiv:1512.00012 [astro-ph]. YITP-SB-15-43.
- 13. Asher Berlin, Dan Hooper, and SDM. Dark matter elastic scattering through Higgs loops. Phys. Rev. D **92**, no. 12, 123531 (2015). arXiv:1508.05390 [hep-ph]. YITP-SB-15-29.
- 12. Hooman Davoudiasl, Dan Hooper, and SDM. *Inflatable Dark Matter*. Phys. Rev. Lett. **116**, 031303 (2016); selected as an **Editor's Choice** article. arXiv:1507.08660 [hep-ph]. YITP-SB-15-26.
- 11. Vera Gluscevic, Moira Gresham, SDM, Annika H. G. Peter, and Kathryn M. Zurek. *Identifying the Theory of Dark Matter with Direct Detection*. JCAP **12**, 12, 057 (2015). arXiv:1506.04454 [hep-ph]. YITP-SB-15-16. Associated code publicly available on github and ASCL.

Prepared while at Fermilab as a Fermilab Fellow:

- 10. SDM. Lining up the Galactic Center Gamma-Ray Excess. Phys. Dark Univ. 7-8, 12 (2015). arXiv:1406.6408 [hep-ph]. FERMILAB-PUB-14-205-A-T.
- 9. Asher Berlin, Pierre Gratia, Dan Hooper, and SDM. *Hidden Sector Dark Matter Models for the Galactic Center Gamma-Ray Excess*. Phys. Rev. D **90**, 015032 (2014). arXiv:1405.5204 [hep-ph]. MCTP-14-12, FERMILAB-PUB-14-134-A.
- 8. Asher Berlin, Dan Hooper, and SDM. Simplified Dark Matter Models for the Galactic Center Gamma-Ray Excess. Phys. Rev. D 89, 115022 (2014). arXiv:1404.0022 [hep-ph]. MCTP-14-07, FERMILAB-PUB-14-060-A.

7. Ilias Cholis, Dan Hooper, and SDM. Dissecting the Gamma-Ray Background in Search of Dark Matter. JCAP **02**, 014 (2014). arXiv:1312.0608 [astro-ph]. MCTP-13-40, FERMILAB-PUB-13-546-A.

Rouven Essig, Eric Kuflik, SDM, Tomer Volansky, and Kathryn M. Zurek. Constraining Light Dark Matter with Diffuse X-Ray and Gamma-Ray Observations.
JHEP 11, 193 (2013). arXiv:1309.4091 [hep-ph]. MCTP-13-27, FERMILAB-PUB-13-377-A-T.

Prepared while a graduate student at the University of Michigan and a member of the Michigan Center for Theoretical Physics (MCTP):

- Clifford Cheung, SDM, and Kathryn M. Zurek. Inspecting the Higgs for New Weakly Interacting Particles. JHEP 04, 074 (2013). arXiv:1302.0314 [hep-ph]. MCTP-13-01.
- 4. Eric Kuflik, SDM, and Kathryn M. Zurek. Neutrino Phenomenology in a 3+1+1 Framework. Phys. Rev. D 86, 033015 (2012). arXiv:1205.1791 [hep-ph]. MCTP-12-11.
- 3. SDM, Hai-Bo Yu, and Kathryn M. Zurek. *The Dark Matter Inverse Problem:* Extracting Particle Physics from Scattering Events. Phys. Rev. D **85**, 123507 (2012). arXiv:1110.4281 [hep-ph]. MCTP-11-34.
- SDM, Hai-Bo Yu, and Kathryn M. Zurek. Constraints on Scalar Asymmetric Dark Matter from Black Hole Formation in Neutron Stars. Phys. Rev. D 85, 023519 (2012). arXiv:1103.5472 [hep-ph]. MCTP-11-16.
- 1. SDM, Hai-Bo Yu, and Kathryn M. Zurek. *Turning off the Lights: How Dark is Dark Matter?* Phys. Rev. D **83**, 063509 (2011). arXiv:1011.2907 [hep-ph]. MCTP-10-52.

Code

I have the following programming language skills

- **Proficiency:** Mathematica, Python, HTML
- Familiarity: Cython, CSS

In addition, I co-authored the code package dmdd, ascl:1506.002

- dmdd is a python package that enables simple simulation and Bayesian posterior analysis of nuclear-recoil data from dark matter direct detection experiments for a wide variety of theories of dark matter-nucleon interactions. dmdd was developed in collaboration with Vera Gluscevic for use in arXiv:1506.04454, additionally with Moira Gresham, Annika H. G. Peter, and Kathryn M. Zurek.
- dmdd was used by the PICO collaboration to set official limits in arXiv:1510.07754 [hep-ex]

Colloquia and New Physics at the Stellar Frontier

SUMMARY TALKS

Argonne National Laboratory Physics Division
 University of Utah Department of Physics & Astronomy
 King's College London Theoretical Particle Physics & Cosmology
 Oct 25, 2021

• King's College London Theoretical Particle Physics & Cosmology Stellar Probes of New Physics Topical Review

• Brookhaven Forum 2021 **Nov 3, 2021** 

Hunting for Dark Matter in the Lab, the Galaxy, and the Universe

• University of Victoria Department of Physics & Astronomy Mar 9, 2020

INVITED TALKS Assorted topics: (\*REMOTE) • Carnegie Mellon University Stellar Tests of Gravity Workshop Mar 18 2022 4D Seminar, University of California Berkeley Feb 14, 2022 \*Carleton HEP Seminar Nov 8, 2021 \*INT Workshop Sept 21, 2021 Sept 14, 2021 \*BSM PANDEMIC Series • \*Particles and Nuclei International Conference Sept 8, 2021 • \*Cambridge (Mass.) High Energy Workshop 2021 - Axion Physics July 28, 2021 • \*APS DPF 2021 July 13, 2021 • \*The 16th Marcel Grossman Meeting July 8, 2021 \*Cosmology from Home July 7, 2021 Apr 1, 2021 • \*A Rainbow of Dark Sectors, Aspen Center for Physics • \*HEP Seminar, UC Santa Barbara Nov 16, 2020 • \*APEC Seminar, Kavli IPMU Oct 21, 2020 • \*SITP Seminar, Stanford University Oct 15, 2020 • \*High Energy Theory Seminar, Brown University Oct 14, 2020 Oct 12, 2020 • \*High Energy Physics Seminar, Caltech • \*Perimeter Institute Seminar Apr 28, 2020 • \*MCFP Seminar, University of Maryland Mar 26, 2020 • \*Theory Seminar, Notre Dame Feb 23, 2020 • \*N3AS Seminar Feb 2, 2020 \*Israeli Joint Particle Physics Seminar, Hebrew University Jun 24, 2020 \*Thursday Seminar, CERN Th Mar 19, 2020 • New Techniques for Dark Matter Discovery, TRIUMF Mar 12, 2020 CCPP Seminar, New York University Jan 31, 2020 YITP-Brookhaven Joint Seminar, Stony Brook University Jan 29, 2020 • Informal Seminar, Harvard University Jan 24, 2020 • Nuclear Theory Seminar, University of Kentucky Dec 19, 2019 • Nuclear and Particle Theory Seminar, MIT Oct 28, 2019 • Exceptional Seminar, CERN Th Sept 30, 2019 CCPP Seminar, New York University Feb 9, 2019 Brown Bag Seminar, University of Michigan Oct 31, 2018 Cosmic Controversies, KICP Oct 7, 2019 • No Stone Unturned Workshop, Utah Aug 7, 2019 • Current Trends in Particle Theory, UIC June 16, 2019 • AAS Dark Matter "Meeting within a Meeting" June 11, 2019 • LSST Dark Matter Workshop, KICP Aug 5, 2019 • multiple, Aspen Center for Physics 2015, 2016, 2017, and 2019 Seventh PIMKIO meeting, University of Michigan March 29, 2019 Theory Seminar, Argonne National Lab April 9, 2019 Twelfth Conference on the Identification of Dark Matter July 23, 2018 May 30 and 31, 2018 CIPANP XIII Theoretical Astrophysics Seminar, Fermilab May 21, 2018 • Kavli Institute for Theoretical Physics Apr 10, 2018 Theoretical Physics Seminar, Brandeis University Feb 15, 2018 Theoretical Astrophysics Seminar, Fermilab Feb 5, 2018 Particle Theory Seminar, Perimeter Institute Dec 1, 2017 • HPS Collaboration Telecon Nov 15, 2017 • Particle Physics Seminar, University of Washington Oct 24, 2017

• ITS Seminar, University of Oregon	Oct 23, 2017
• Theory Seminar, SLAC	Oct 20, 2017
• 4D Seminar, Berkeley	Oct 18, 2017
• Particle Theory Seminar, Boston University	Oct 11, 2017
• CFP Seminar, University of Maryland	Apr $10, 2017$
• Nuclear Theory Seminar, University of Kentucky	Apr $6, 2017$
• High Energy Theory Seminar, University of Minnesota	Mar 10, 2017
• HEP Seminar, Johns Hopkins University	Oct 25, 2016
• Dark Interactions Workshop, Brookhaven	Sep 7, 2016
• Joint Particle Seminar, UC Irvine	Apr 27, 2016
• High Energy Physics Seminar, Caltech	Apr 25, 2016
• Astro Coffee, IAS	Feb 3, 2016
• Pheno & Vino, Princeton	Feb 2, 2016
• Galileo Galilei Institute workshop	Sep $30, 2015$
• APS DPF meeting, Ann Arbor	Aug 5, 2015
• URA Thesis Award Presentation, Fermilab Users Meeting	June 10, 2015
• Cornell Particle Theory Seminar	Apr $10, 2015$
• Maryland CFP	Mar 9, 2015
• Brookhaven National Lab	Mar 4, 2015
• UT Austin Theory Group Seminar	Nov 4, 2014
• IAS Astro Coffee	Oct 8, 2014
• MIT CTP	Oct 1, 2014
• Université de Montréal and McGill dark matter workshop	July 24, 2014
• University of Chicago Dark Matter Hub meeting	Apr 15, 2014
• Los Alamos T2 Seminar	Dec 5, 2013
• Wisconsin Theory Seminar	Nov 8, 2013
• SLAC Theoretical Physics Seminar	Oct 30, 2013
• Fermilab Theory Seminar	Oct 17, 2013

In addition, I have given parallel and other talks at the Midwest Relativity Meeting, FNAL, Brookhaven Forum, YITP, COSMO2014, TeVPA/IDM 2014, the Pitt Phenomenology meetings, and the 19th SUSY meeting

# Professional Service

Referee: Phys. Rev. Letters, the Astrophysical Journal, MNRAS Letters, JHEP, Phys. Rev. D, and Phys. Letters B.

Organizer of the following conferences, workshops, and meetings:

- Dark Matter in Compact Objects, Stars, and in Low Energy Experiments (22-2b) (Aug 1- Sep 2, 2022) at the University of Washington's Institute for Nuclear Theory; inclusive of a \$106,400 grant from the Institute for Nuclear Theory
- Next Frontiers in the Search for Dark Matter (Aug 26 Oct 11, 2019) at Galileo Galilei Institute in Arcetri, Italy; inclusive of a five-day conference
- New Directions in the Search for Light Dark Matter Particles (June 4-7, 2019) at Fermilab and KICP; awarded \$24,525 grant from the Gordon and Betty Moore Foundation
- Beyond WIMPs: from Theory to Detection (March 27-29, 2017) at the Simons Center for Geometry and Physics
- Light Dark Matter: Asymmetric, thermal and non-thermal dark matter and its detection (April, 2013) at the Michigan Center for Theoretical Physics

Press

Hershberger, Scott. "Physics at Tiniest Scale Could Explain 'Impossible' Black Holes" Symmetry Magazine, 16 December 2020.

Hershberger, Scott. "If Betelgeuse goes boom: How DUNE would respond to a nearby supernova." Fermilab News, 5 October 2020.

Sakstein, Jeremy and Croon, Djuna, and SDM. "Beyond the Standard Model Explanations of GW190521." Newsletter of the CERN Experimental Physics Department, 29 September 2020.

Hekkenberg, Ans. "Overschot straling centrum Melkweg niet te verklaren met donkere materie" (Dutch) newscientist.nl, 8 September 2020.

Fadelli, Ingrid. "Could recently spotted dim point sources explain the galactic center excess (GCE)?" *Phys.org*, 14 July 2020.

Muñoz, Julian and Loeb, Abraham. "The First Stars May Shed Light on Dark Matter." *APS Physics*, 2 July 2018.

Conover, Emily. "If real, dark fusion could help demystify this physics puzzle." *Science News*, 6 June 2018.

Inglis-Arkell, Esther. "'Inflatable Dark Matter' Could Explain Why We See Less Than Many Theories Predict." *Gizmodo*, 18 January 2016.